<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Programming | Luke Gorrie's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.lukego.com//blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.lukego.com//"/>
  <updated>2013-06-23T14:31:02+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.lukego.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Luke Gorrie]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cute code]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.lukego.com//blog/2013/02/04/cute-code/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-04T15:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.lukego.com//blog/2013/02/04/cute-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today was one of those pleasant days when I know it's not the time for serious programming.</p>

<p>I had a lovely twitter conversation with <a href="http://twitter.com/tapoueh">Dimitri Fontaine</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/fanf">Tony Finch</a>, and <a href="http://twitter.com/janl">Jan Lehnardt</a>. I started out wanting to recommend a data structure to <a href="https://github.com/rahul-mr">@rahul-mr</a> for easily garbage collecting <a href="http://snabb.co/snabbswitch/">Snabb Switch</a>'s ethernet forwarding table. Trouble is, I don't know the name of the data structure, so I posted this implementation in <a href="https://gist.github.com/4706097">a gist</a> and asked if anybody knows what it's called. Here's the code:</p>

<p>```lua
-- Table structure that "garbage collects" not-recently-used items in O(1) time.</p>

<p>-- Three operations are supported:
--   insert(k,v): add a new value
--   lookup(k): lookup an existing value
--   age(): delete old entries (that have not been used since previous call to age())</p>

<p>-- Initialize 'old' and 'new' to empty tables
local old, new = {}, {}</p>

<p>function insert(k, v)
  new[k] = v
end</p>

<p>function lookup(k)
  if new[k] then</p>

<pre><code>-- Found in new table
return new[k]
</code></pre>

<p>  elseif old[k] then</p>

<pre><code>-- Migrate from old table to new table
new[k] = old[k]
return old[k]
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>-- Not found
return nil
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>function age()
  -- Entries in 'old' are dropped, entries in 'new' become old.
  old = new
  new = {} -- empty table
end
```</p>

<p>And the twitterverse helped me rewrite this much more concisely:</p>

<p><code>lua
local old, new = {}, {}
function insert(k, v) new[k] = v; return v               end
function lookup(k)    return new[k] or insert(k, old[k]) end
function age()        old, new = new, {}                 end
</code></p>

<p>which I find rather aesthetically satisfying.</p>

<p>Rewriting code more concisely is one of my favorite activities. Lisp is my usual tool of choice for this purpose, so I tried a translation just for fun:</p>

<p>```common-lisp
(defvar <em>new</em> (make-hash-table))
(defvar <em>old</em> (make-hash-table))</p>

<p>(defun insert (k v)
  (when v (setf (gethash <em>new</em> k) v)))</p>

<p>(defun lookup (k v)
  (or (gethash <em>new</em> k) (insert k (gethash <em>old</em> k))))</p>

<p>(defun age ()
  (rotatef <em>old</em> <em>new</em>)
  (clrhash <em>new</em>))
```</p>

<p>and I found it interesting that the Lua version is so much more compact than the Lisp version. Sure, I've compacted it with whitespace tweakery and so on, but each version is as concise as I feel comfortable making it. So I wonder if Lua is becoming my preferred vehicle for writing pseudo-pseudo-code and indulging in cutenesses?</p>

<p>Then having <em>cuteness</em> cross my mind I couldn't help but think back to cute code I've worked on before. I wrote my own favorite bit of cute production code in the OLPC firmware <a href="http://tracker.coreboot.org/trac/openfirmware/browser/dev/hdaudio/core.fth">HD Audio driver</a>. You see, the firmware is allowed to hard-code knowledge of the physical design of the laptop and motherboard. This bit of firmware code tells the audio chip explicit details such as the size and color of each physical audio jack in the laptop. The chip can later provide this information to the operating system for presentation to a user, for example in an audio mixer application.</p>

<p><code>text
porta  config(  1/8" green left hp-out jack     )config
porta  config(  1/8" green left hp-out jack     )config
portb  config(  1/8" pink left mic-in jack      )config
portc  config(  builtin internal top mic-in no-detect other-analog )config
portd  config(  unused line-out no-detect       )config
porte  config(  unused line-out no-detect       )config
portf  config(  unused line-out no-detect       )config
portg  config(  builtin internal front speaker no-detect other-analog )config
porth  config(  unused line-out no-detect       )config
porti  config(  unused line-out no-detect       )config
portj  config(  unused line-out no-detect       )config
portk  config(  unused line-out no-detect       )config
</code></p>

<p>The code reads a bit like english - <em>1/8" pink left mic-in jack</em> - but is actually purely imperative Forth code that was inspired by the wonderful book <a href="http://thinking-forth.sourceforge.net">Thinking Forth</a>.</p>

<p>So it goes!</p>

<p>P.S. I never did work out the canonical name of the data structure. Please drop me an email on <code>luke@snabb.co</code> if you know.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/lukego" class="twitter-follow-button" data-show-count="false">Follow @lukego</a></p>

<script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Readable programs]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.lukego.com//blog/2012/10/24/readable-programs/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-24T17:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.lukego.com//blog/2012/10/24/readable-programs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love readable programs. I mean: programs that you can print out, take to the park, and read from top to bottom. The reason I love readable programs is that somebody has made the effort to make them readable, perhaps simply by priting them out and running through them with a red pen a few times, and I believe this simple process to have a magical effect on a program's clarity.</p>

<p>I believe that making programs readable is one of the best and easiest ways to improve them.</p>

<p>I gather that it used to be a common practice to print program listings and read them. I hear about it in anecdotes from programmers I respect, and I also see that many older programs appear to have been written with printing and readnig in mind: they contain pagebreak characters; they include their user-documentation in comments; and they are broken into logical sections of a couple of pages or so.</p>

<p>Let me share some quotations that have stuck in my memory:</p>

<blockquote><p>The mask layout program by BillCroft at Purdue EE department - This
is a truly awesome C program that could do VLSI scale designs on a
PDP-11. The implementation included the command processing,
high-resolution graphics, and custom database. Amazingly the program
was only about half an inch thick and could be read in an afternoon.
(Contrast this to my own companies' graphics drivers for the same
device which ran ten times this for the drivers alone.)</p></blockquote>

<p>-- <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?PleaseShowMeAlargeWellFactoredProgram">Ward Cunningham, WardsWiki</a></p>

<blockquote><p>I was the one who decided to rewrite the [program listing generator]
from scratch as a standalone program, partly because I wanted to add
substantial new facilities, such as the ability to list many files at
once and provide inter-file cross-references.</p></blockquote>

<p>-- <a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/gregs/ll1-discuss-archive-html/msg02724.html">Guy Steele, ll1-discuss</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Programming is, among other things, a kind of writing. One way to
learn writing is to write, but in all other forms of writing, one also
reads. We read examples - both good and bad - to facilitate learning.
But how many programmers learn to write programs by reading programs?
A few, but not many. And with the advent of terminals, things are
getting worse, for the programmer may not even see his own program in
a form suitable for reading. In the old days ... programmers would
while away the time by reading each others' programs. Some even went
so far as to read programs from the program library - which in those
days was still a library in the old sense of the term.</p></blockquote>

<p>-- <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Psychology-Computer-Programming-Anniversary/dp/0932633420">Gerald Weinberg, The Psychology of Computer Programming</a></p>

<p>How different things used to be. People measured programs in "thickness", wrote special listing generators (in <a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/gregs/ll1-discuss-archive-html/msg02718.html">300 pages of PDP-10 assembler</a> - quite an effort), and dreaded that one day people may not sit down and read programs, not even their own.</p>

<p>I know it's easy to feel that with our fancy IDEs we've advanced beyond such archaic ideas, but I believe that reading whole programs is a Good Thing and worth holding on to.</p>

<p>I've done a few experiments with readable programs over the years. The first one was about 10 years ago, a program listing generator called <a href="http://discontinuity.info/~pkhuong/pbookc.pdf">pbook.el</a>. pbook itself actually sucks - it's way too much code and way too much commentary - but <a href="http://fresh.homeunix.net/~luke/misc/erlang/regtest.pdf">regtest.erl</a> is one reasonable example use from my professional life. I wrote another listing generator called <code>elit.el</code> that was intended to mimic Steele's style with RABBIT but this program sucked too for the same reasons. I'm not sure that listing generators are really needed, at least for short programs like <a href="http://fresh.homeunix.net/~luke/misc/python/bets.py.txt">bets.py</a>. Early versions of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SLIME">SLIME</a> were quietly pbook-formatted and I used to read them through without mentioning it to anybody.</p>

<p>So why blog about this now?</p>

<p>I'm working on a new project called <a href="http://www.github.com/SnabbCo/snabbswitch/">Snabb Switch</a>. I want the Snabb Switch code to be really good, so I'm very tempted to make it readable. I'm starting to think about what could be a practical tool for generating a program listing roughly the size of a small book, with chapters like "Intel NIC device driver", "OpenFlow forwarding engine", and so on.</p>

<p>The idea I'm playing with at the moment is to have a 'make' target to publish the Snabb Switch on <a href="http://www.leanpub.com/">Leanpub</a>. This way I can calmly read through my source code with a red pen on my train rides between Zurich and the Alps. I expect that this would increase the quality of my source code overall and be well worth the effort, quite independent of whether other people decide to read the program too.</p>

<p>I've at least made one pleasing discovery: thanks to the beauty of Markdown I'm now able to write a version of pbook that is down from 241 lines to a mere 43 characters: <code>sed -E -e 's/^/    /g' -e 's/^    --- ?//g'</code>. (See my <a href="https://gist.github.com/3945964">Gist</a> for a few more details.)</p>

<p>So that is my brain dump for today. Are you also interested in readable programs? Feel free to strike up a conversation with me on <code>luke@snabb.co</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
