<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: snabb | Luke Gorrie's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.lukego.com//blog/categories/snabb/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.lukego.com//"/>
  <updated>2013-04-03T15:35:30+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.lukego.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Luke Gorrie]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Snabb - my lab]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.lukego.com//blog/2013/04/03/snabb-my-lab/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-03T14:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.lukego.com//blog/2013/04/03/snabb-my-lab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love my little company, <a href="http://snabb.co/">Snabb</a>. It is <a href="http://sivers.org/laboratory">my laboratory</a>.</p>

<p>My lab makes me productive in society. I write really cool open source code for anybody to use, and I earn money by traveling around <strong>meeting interesting people</strong> and helping them to solve important problems. I have "hard fun" looking for ways to do these things in harmony.</p>

<p>My lab is where I can <strong>be creative</strong>. I can ask myself, after 25 years of thoughtful programming, <em>what's the right way to do fast ethernet I/O?</em> and then develop my answer: a small <a href="https://github.com/SnabbCo/snabbswitch/blob/master/src/intel10g.lua">10G Ethernet device driver</a> written in LuaJIT and embedded in the application. Fun!</p>

<p>My lab lets me <strong>work with friendly people</strong> in the open source world. I get to take part in the conversation on how to write networking software, and I can collaborate on equal footing with other clever hackers who have their own interests and labs, big and small.</p>

<p>My lab lets me <strong>buy fun toys</strong> (without asking permission :-)). Any day now I will receive a <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!topic/snabb-devel/vUd2DZZ-ctw">server with twenty 10G ethernet ports</a> to share with everybody hacking on the <a href="http://snabb.co/snabbswitch/">Snabb Switch</a> project. We get to break new ground together in the spirit of creative fun.</p>

<p>My lab lets me create software of <strong>enduring value</strong>. I do not have to constrain my code with secrecy and license restrictions, which means that it can take on a life of its own. The software can follow its own strong tendency to spread and thrive. I have just given a talk about SLIME at the first Emacs conference -- 10-year-old work on a 37-year-old editor and still in widespread use!</p>

<p>My lab lets me <strong>choose</strong> to do all of these things, all by myself, and it would let me choose to do something completely different if that was what I wanted. It lets me decide when to work from my house in the Swiss Alps, a beach in Thailand, my family's home in Australia, a cosy cafe in a big city, or a friendly office. It makes me abundantly wealthy in freedom and independence.</p>

<p>In summary I feel that I am close to a local maximum for <strong>creativity and freedom</strong>.</p>

<p>The problem has never been to "make" the company a success, but rather to <strong>preserve</strong> the great situation that I already had from the first day. On the one hand I need to avoid things like running out of money, selling shares, and signing employment contracts, and on the other hand I need to keep writing cool open source software and finding people with important problems I can help with. This way I can keep on being <a href="http://us1.campaign-archive2.com/?u=ebf088d153799238adff7f681&amp;id=5e842b4e52">proud</a> of my company.</p>

<blockquote>
A man is a success if he wakes up in the morning and goes to bed at night and in between does what he wants to do.- Bob Dylan
</blockquote>


<p>Know what I mean? I would be happy to <strong>hear from you</strong> on luke@snabb.co.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
